Register of the Okhrana records
Hoover Institution Archives
- V. Liaison (Boxes 34-37, 239-241)
  - b. Relations with the French Sûreté (Boxes 34-35, 239-241)
    The Okhrana's relations with the French Sûreté Générale and other government organs were subject to greater rises and falls in the degree of cooperation than in any other country. Intense campaigns of the revolutionaries in emigration and the supporting liberal press of France often led to attacks upon the French Parliament, with repercussions in executive arms of the government, and thus to cooling-off periods in the Okhrana-Sûreté liaison. Invariably, the efforts of the chief in Paris, state visits, some outrageous act of terror, or other causes cemented the relations again into close and, at times, truly amicable relations.
    Folders 3 and 4 contain documents related to the liaison activity exchange of information and assistance in operations against the revolutionaries. Folder 5 contains mostly dispatches between Headquarters and the Paris Office, dealing for the most part with instructions, and suggestions regarding French liaison.
    Other materials in these folders are mostly informative. The Okhrana Office kept the annuals of the French Sûreté, information on Sûreté personnel and functions for reference purposes. Some of the documents show that the Okhrana made background and character studies of French officials with whom it intended to seek cooperation. The three volumes with mounted photographs on terrorist construction use of bombs, one containing illustrations from Russian techniques, are indicative that these materials were exchanged in liaison for training purposes.
    Much of the liaison exchange with the Sûreté was carried out by the office of Marcel Bittard-Monin, the Okhrana's principal agent in charge of non-Russian operatives. He and several of his subordinates were former Sûreté officials or agents. As such, they were particularly well qualified for liaison with former colleagues at almost any level of the Sûreté or police departments. The advantage of having access to police records at various local levels was realized much before the engagement of Bittard-Monin. The many thousands of biographic notes prepared in the 1890s and early 1900s by agent Fehrenbach were copied from the various police records to which he had access in Paris as in many other communities of France.
    Available on microfilm reels 67-69
    - Annals of the French Sûreté, 1910 and 1914; 1 set of addresses of police officers in Paris; 1 chart on the police network in Paris; 7 reports on French statesmen (1882-1887); and 3 old warrants from the Paris police (1858-1905), 1858-1914 (Index Vb, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence referring to decorations and gifts to French Sûreté officials, 1886-1916 (Index Vb, Folder 2)
      Available on microfilm reel 68
    - Correspondence of the Paris Okhrana with the French Sûreté, 1887-1916 (Index Vb, Folder 3)
    - Cooperation of the French Sûreté with the Paris Okhrana, 1887-1916 (Index Vb, Folder 4)
    - Dispatches and notes exhanged between Headquarters and the Paris office, 1893-1917 (Index Vb, Folder 5)
      Available on microfilm reel 69
    - Books prepared by the French Sûreté with graphic illustrations for training French policemen on the methods of the terrorists, 1884-1894 (Index Vb, Folder 6)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index Vb, Folder 7)
    - Reference: For receipts for decorations, signed by French officials, see IVb (Index Vb, Folder 8)
    - Reference: See outgoing telegram, April 16, 1904, reporting that Delcasse has given information about a possible assassination attempt on a Russian minister, in XIIIb(2), folder 3. (Index Vb, Folder 9)
  - c. Relations with Scotland Yard (Box 35)
    Liaison with Scotland Yard and other organs in Great Britain differed significantly from the liaison with the French Sûreté. There were no ups and downs or cooling-off periods, but a steady businesslike cooperation. If at all affected by the virulent attacks upon the Okhrana by such staunch and usually respectable supporters as Prince Kropotkin and his "school" or the Jewish Bund in London, the available documents do not show it. In fact, the Okhrana's liaison with the British improved over time, particularly when war broke out. Chief Krasil'nikov's friendly correspondence with Chief Quinn of Scotland Yard shows close and genuine cooperation.
    Close liaison developed especially after 1912. Several of the Okhrana's British agents in London had passed away. Krasil'nikov approached Quinn to designate a capable British person to run the British agents in the surveillance of Russians in England. After due deliberation of some months, Quinn recommended one of his beat inspectors, Francis Powell, who by the end of that year became the principal agent for England. His assisting agents were all former Scotland Yard men.
    Supplementary information to the contents of the folders in this collection may be found in file IIb (London outpost) and the folders on agent Powell in IIIe and VIk.
    - Correspondence between Headquarters and the Paris office, 1890-1916 (Index Vc, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence between the London police and the Paris Okhrana, 1897-1915 (Index Vc, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence between the Paris Okhrana and the London police, 1897-1916 (Index Vc, Folder 3)
    - Samples of agents' reports from London, 1907-1916 (Index Vc, Folder 4)
    - Lists of British police officials recommended for decorations, 1907-1909 (Index Vc, Folder 5)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index Vc, Folder 6)
    - Reference: For address book of foreign security officials, see Va, folder 7 (Index Vc, Folder 7)
    - Reference: For agent Farce's reports from London on penetration of Scotland Yard by the Okhrana in 1905, see VIIIa (Index Vc, Folder 8)
    - Reference: For agent Thorpe's letters from London on cooperation with the London police, 1907-1908, see VIIIa (Index Vc, Folder 9)
    - Reference: For cooperation with Scotland Yard on the Houndsditch robbery by the anarchists, see XVIb(5), folder 1 (Index Vc, Folder 10)
  - d. Relations with the German Sicherheit (Boxes 35-36)
    Because of the German federal system, a centralized liaison as in England and France could not be established. An outstanding and long term contact was maintained with the police directorate in Berlin, the head of which, Wilhelm Henninger, maintained almost regular correspondence with the Okhrana chief in Paris. The contents of his intelligence and operational notes do not reveal that he was himself a high level Okhrana agent, but they illustrate amply that he must have been a sizeable recipient of the Okhrana's benefits.
    There were close relations also with police chiefs controlling special political departments in Munich, Darmstadt, and Hamburg. As far as the Okhrana was concerned, Berlin and the Prussian Sicherheitsdienst were the key liaison targets, not so much because of the concentration of the revolutionaries there, but because of the proximity of the Russian borders and overland routes for subversives, arms and literature smugglers, and terrorists.
    Close cooperation in Berlin was partly the result of Garting's early efforts. He was chief of the Okhrana agentura there from 1901 to 1905 and was accredited as such by the Germans. They caused him some trouble when it was made known that, apart from liaison, Garting had under him also some German agents, but the affair was straightened out after Garting's assignment to Paris.
    Folder 1, assorted only chronologically, contains correspondence with a large number of city and state police directorates, including samples of exchanged information on revolutionaries, smugglers of arms (Hamburg), apprehension of revolutionary bandits with marked bank notes (Munich, Berlin). Folder 2 has dispatches with Headquarters, dealing with liaison, while the lists of officers named for decorations and awards include primarily people on both sides of the liaison, cooperating in various tasks.
    Available on microfilm reels 70-71
    - Letters regarding correspondence with German police in various cities, including police director Henninger in Berlin and chiefs in Munich, Darmstadt, Frankfurt, etc., 1899-1914 (Index Vd, Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 70
    - Dispatches between Headquarters and the Paris office regarding cooperation with the German police, 1901-1916 (Index Vd, Folder 2)
    - Decorations and awards for German police officials, 1890-1913 (Index Vd, Folder 3)
    - Coordination with German security for measures taken to guard traveling Imperial majesties, 1910 (Index Vd, Folder 4)
      Available on microfilm reel 71
    - Drafts and letters referring to smuggling of arms into Russia, 1906 (Index Vd, Folder 5)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index Vd, Folder 6)
    - Reference: See incoming 1904 telegram commenting on an article in Petite République denying any role in the arrests of socialists in Germany, in XIIIc(3), folder 16 (Index Vd, Folder 7)
    - Reference: For intelligence reports on arms shipments from Germany, 1906, see XXIVh (Index Vd, Folder 8)
  - e. Relations with the Italian Sicurezza (Box 36)
    The Okhrana's cooperation with the Italian police, intelligence, and diplomatic authorities was both overt and secret. Italy, too, was a signatory to the St. Petersburg treaty for cooperation in the suppression of subversives, and the number of Italian anarchists named in Okhrana Headquarters warning lists and on biographic cards is considerable. (Even the name of the young Benito Mussolini came into the Okhrana records.)
    In Paris, liaison with the Italians was first made through the Embassy, and cooperation with the Italian Military Attaché, Wenzel (probably in the Okhrana's pay), was particularly active until his expulsion from Paris. The documents coming from the Rome and other questuras are illustrative of the exchange of information. The arrangement of Okhrana representatives with Italian local authorities, particularly the post offices in the towns of the Italian Riviera, for mail intercepts were clandestine and of course illegal, ending at times in scandal that had to be aired in the Rome parliament.
    - Correspondence between Headquarters and the Paris office, 1906-1916 (Index Ve, Folder 1)
    - Dispatches relating to cooperation with the Italian authorities, 1902-1916 (Index Ve, Folder 2)
    - Decorations and rewards for Italian police officials, 1909-1912 (Index Ve, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with the Italian military attaché, 1909-1911 (Index Ve, Folder 4)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index Ve, Folder 5)
  - f. Relations with police of other countries (Boxes 36-37)
    Available on microfilm reels 71-73
    - Austria
      Despite the fact that Austria-Hungary was partner in the pact for cooperation in combatting international terrorists, there is little trace of any liaison between the Okhrana and the Austrian services. The folders include a set of letters in which information is exchanged with the Vienna police directorate about subversives, but no instance is on record, as in the liaison with the Prussian Sicherheit, of cooperation in detecting and apprehending smugglers of bombs and terrorists on the border. As a matter of record, the Galician border was a favorite spot for illegal crossing along the Prussian border; yet, while at the latter locations, the Okhrana could frequently count on German assistance, it had to rely upon its own resources for tailing and apprehending terrorists crossing the Austrian borders.
      The lack of cooperation with Austria may be attributed to mutual suspicion. Both countries had rebellious minority nationalities, and it appears that neither was unhappy over the other's problems on the identical issue. To add fuel to this embryonic cold war situation, the Okhrana frequently detected Austrian agents crossing Into Russia. (See the files on pre-World War I counter-espionage under Index Number VIIIa.)
      - Dispatches relating to cooperation, 1886-1913 (Index Vf, Folder 1)
      - Cooperation between the Vienna police and the Paris Okhrana, 1896-1914 (Index Vf, Folder 2)
      - Drafts of letters (Index Vf, Folder 3)
      - Cross-reference sheet (Index Vf, Folder 4)
      - Reference: For address book of foreign security officials, see Va, folder 7 (Index Vf, Folder 5)
    - Belgium
      The lively liaison of the Okhrana with the Belgian services had its beginnings in the mid-1890s, after the marriage of Garting, later Okhrana chief in Berlin and then Paris, to a Belgian socialite and noblewoman. Garting,an Okhrana agent since 1890, became influential among the important government circles and thus did more to insure a steady exchange of information, essentially at the top level of the country's services. Most of the bulky intelligence correspondence of the Paris Okhrana with Belgium is thus through the Director of the Sûreté Publique in the Brussels Ministry of Justice.
      From the standpoint of Okhrana operations abroad, Brussels and the Belgian ports were of primary importance since much of the smuggling of arms, forbidden literature, and conspirators en route to Russia went through Belgian ports.
      - Correspondence with the Belgian police, requesting data on Russian revolutionaries, 1896-1914 (Index Vf, Folder 1)
      - Information on Russian revolutionaries and their organizations sent by the Belgian police, 1904-1917 (Index Vf, Folder 2)
        Available on microfilm reel 72
      - Correspondence between Headquarters and the Paris office, 1906-1913 (Index Vf, Folder 3)
      - Reports from Paris Okhrana agents working in Belgium, 1910 (Index Vf, Folder 4)
      - Decorations and rewards for Belgian police officials, 1896 (Index Vf, Folder 5)
      - Undated notes on Russian individuals (Index Vf, Folder 6)
      - Cross-reference sheet (Index Vf, Folder 7)
      - Reference: For address book of foreign security officials, see Va, folder 7 (Index Vf, Folder 8)
      - Reference: See report from the Russian consulate in Antwerp, February 4, 1905, in Vg. (Index Vf, Folder 9)
    - Switzerland
      The documents in Folder 1 contain some correspondence with the chiefs of the Swiss federal services, indicating some liaison and resulting exchanges of information at that level. The major part of cooperation, however, was at the canton and municipal police levels at Bern, Zurich, Geneva, Lausanne, and several minor communities. The most productive in obtaining intelligence on the activities of Russian conspirators, residing in considerable numbers in Switzerland,was the liaison on strictly local levels. Thousands of reports submitted by agents Bint, Woltz, and others from various Swiss cities from 1900 to 1915 are copies from the local Swiss police registers. Their access to information was on a personal, friendship, or business basis, but some intermediary through liaison at a slightly higher level than the police station counter may be spotted in the correspondence collected in the two folders. Sometimes, the liaison on this local, agent basis went even a step further. A police official was placed on the Okhrana payroll, supplying not only information on revolutionaries but assisting in operations against them. (Example: See the folder on agent Treichler, police official in Zurich, in Ille, Folder 3.)
      - Dispatches related to cooperation between the Swiss police and the Paris Okhrana, 1895-1915 (Index Vf, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence between Headquarters and the Paris office related to cooperation with the Swiss authorities, including the case of the extradition of Burtsev and Krakov, 1894-1915 (Index Vf, Folder 2)
      - Cross-reference sheet (Index Vf, Folder 3)
      - Reference: For address book of foreign security officials, see Va, folder 7 (Index Vf, Folder 4)
    - Denmark, 1893-1916 (Index Vf, Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 73
    - Holland, 1894-1911 (Index Vf, Folder 2)
    - Hungary, 1908-1914 (Index Vf, Folder 3)
    - Monaco, 1907-1914 (Index Vf, Folder 4)
    - Romania, 1905-1916 (Index Vf, Folder 5)
    - Serbia, 1914 (Index Vf, Folder 6)
    - Spain, 1906-1913 (Index Vf, Folder 7)
    - Sweden, 1904-1910 (Index Vf, Folder 8)
    - Turkey, 1894-1903 (Index Vf, Folder 9)
    - United States, 1910, 1913 (Index Vf, Folder 10)
    - Reference: For address book of foreign security officials, see Va, folder 7 (Index Vf, Folder 11)
    - Reference: For two letters sent from Sambain reporting on his talks with security chiefs in Stockholm, in June 1916, see XIc(1) (Index Vf, Folder 12)
    - Reference: For responses in "Free Russia" and other press to the pending United States-Russia pact on the extradition of terrorists, 1893, see XVIa (Index Vf, Folder 13)
  - g. Relations with missions abroad (Box 37)
    The Okhrana office in Paris was located at all times in the same complex of buildings as the Imperial Embassy; the agentura in Berlin was in the house of the Imperial Consulate, and, when its staff representatives were on duty in other capitals, their office address was that of the respective diplomatic or consular mission. Administratively, Okhrana establishments abroad had nothing else in common with any other Russian mission. Operationally, they were as closed to the offices representing Russia as to any foreign office.
    The correspondence in the folders of this collection does not reveal incidents of serious friction between Okhrana chiefs abroad and the diplomatic and consular representatives. Conferences on individual problems are referred to, such as the Okhrana chief's briefing on current matters. Frequently, the diplomat or consul would inquire about some applicant's loyalty or character record. Normally, inquiries and replies became part of the written record. Both Russian and non-Russian applicants for Okhrana employment usually addressed themselves to the embassy or consular office. Such and similar correspondence was turned over to the attention of the Okhrana. (See Index Nos. VIa and VIb, containing letters of prospective recruits.)
    Relations with the military mission in Paris, particularly after the Allied intelligence was centralized, became close, with daily exchanges of information in matters of counter-espionage as well as other intelligence topics. (See Index No. lIe and VIIIb, on wartime counter-espionage.)
    The four folders in this collection are organized as to separate correspondence with the Russian Embassy and Consulates in France, the military mission in Paris, the imperial missions in other countries, and specially with Russian missions with regard to arms smuggling.
    Available on microfilm reels 73-74
    - Correspondence between the Paris Okhrana and the Russian Embassy and consulates in France, 1887-1917 (Index Vg, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with the Russian military mission in Paris, 1915-1917 (Index Vg, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence of the Paris office with Russian foreign service posts in Stockholm, Copenhagen, and Berlin referring to arms smuggling into Russia, 1905-1906 (Index Vg, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence between the Paris Okhrana and Russian foreign service posts in Austria, Belgium, Denmark, England, Germany, Holland, Italy, Romania, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United States, 1891-1916 (Index Vg, Folder 4)
      Available on microfilm reel 74
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index Vg, Folder 5)
- VI. Personnel administration: agents (Boxes 37-62)
  - a. Recruitment of agents: Russian nationals (Box 37)
    No document in this collection gives comprehensive instructions concerning the recruitment of agents. In many cases, Russian agents abroad, as a rule in the deep cover category for active participation among target groups, were sent to the field by Headquarters or by provincial Okhrana establishments to report directly back to the home units. At first the Paris Okhrana was responsible for them administratively. Gradually, agents were placed under case officers abroad for reporting and other operational control.
    The Paris Office exchanged with Headquarters scores of dispatches concerning agents sent abroad who were considered ill-suited for operations for such assignments, with the result that final authority in recruitment actually came under the Paris Office or its major staff agents running secret operations.
    The dispatches and other papers in Folders 1 and 2 contain communications on individuals offering services or proposed for employment. When an applicant wrote, he received no answer, whether he was considered for employment or not. If the case appeared promising, he was investigated as to his domicile, character, loyalties, or any of the aspects he introduced in his petition. If the investigation agent's report was favorable, the individual was approached casually and clandestinely, according to the circumstances in each case.
    Many documents pertaining to recruitment of agents are located in the agents' dossiers. (See Index No. Illf, Folders 9-36.)
    Available on microfilm reels 74-75
    - Dispatches pertaining to the recruitment of Russian agents, 1889-1910 (Index VIa, Folder 1)
    - Dispatches pertaining to the recruitment of Russian agents, 1910-1916 (Index VIa, Folder 2)
    - Letters from individuals offering their services to the Okhrana, 1886-1916 (Index VIa, Folder 3)
      Available on microfilm reel 75
    - Dispatch from Headquarters with instructions concerning sending an agent to the United States, 1894 (Index VIa, Folder 4)
    - Dispatch concerning the difficulty of recruiting new agents abroad and keeping deep cover agent Weber in London, 1916 (Index VIa, Folder 5)
    - Undated notes, including two letters requesting employment (Index VIa, Folder 6)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index VIa, Folder 7)
    - Reference: See intelligence summary no. 30, April 24, 1903, regarding the hiring of agents by Okhrana offices, in XIIIc(2), folder 2 (Index VIa, Folder 8)
  - b. Recruitment of agents: foreign nationals (Box 38)
    The hiring of foreign nationals was the responsibility of the field establishment. Headquarters, which received many petitions for employment from abroad, abstained from even commenting on their merits, but forwarded all such letters to the Paris Office for consideration. Only in a few instances, as in the case of a Hungarian swindler named "Tulipan" coming with an offer to uncover a major assassination conspiracy, did Headquarters request serious exploration of the case.
    Much of this correspondence came from adventurers and professional job seekers, but the Okhrana could not afford to disregard the offers completely, especially when the offers for employment suggested the uncovering of plots or information convincing enough that the applicant might have access and capability to acquire the desired intelligence information.
    Kany of the offers came from private detectives and people with years of experience in investigation work. If interested, the Okhrana first tried to obtain information from the service with which the applicant had allegedly worked. More often, however, the Okhrana made a direct approach to the chiefs of services when on the lookout for agents with that qualification. Thus, it happened that most of the efficient personnel engaged by the Okhrana abroad were former investigation agents and detectives with various European services.
    Available on microfilm reels 75-77
    - Offers of services to the Okhrana: dispatches on offers received, comments, etc., 1887-1909 (Index VIb, Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reels 75-76
    - Offers of services to the Okhrana: dispatches on offers received, comments, etc., 1910-1916 (Index VIb, Folder 2)
      Available on microfilm reel 76
    - Applications for work with the Okhrana, 1902-1911 (Index VIb, Folder 3)
    - Undated applications for work with the Okhrana (Index VIb, Folder 4)